Guide to the Hussain Sharif Collection AD.MC.138
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Hussain Sharif Collection
1980 – 2017
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Hussain Sharif (Emirati artist, 1961- ) – حسين شريف (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٦١- )
AD.MC.138
1,010 Digital Objects
Hussain Sharif (b. 1961) is a Dubai-based Emirati artist widely considered a pioneer of the contemporary art movement in the UAE. Sharif began his career as a caricature artist in high school and published his work daily or weekly in newspapers across the UAE. In 1980, he was a founding member of the Emirates Fine Arts Society in Sharjah and participated in the association's activities in exhibitions. Sharif received a government scholarship in 1983 to study at the High Institute of Kuwait and graduated in 1986 with a degree in theatre design. Soon after, he accepted a position as head designer at Sharjah TV. Throughout his career, Sharif explored numerous mediums and exhibited his drawings, paintings, collages, and multimedia art installations widely throughout the UAE and internationally, including in Russia, Holland, France, Egypt, and Germany. The Hussain Sharif Collection includes exhibition materials, press clippings, photographic materials, and related items that provide a comprehensive overview of Sharif's artistic practice and the development of the fine art scene in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) from the 1980s to early 2000s. Key highlights of the collection include exhibition catalogs from the annual exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS), such as the catalog for the inaugural exhibition in Abu Dhabi (1980), along with additional catalogs, brochures, and invitations from art exhibitions in the UAE spanning the 1980s to the 2000s. Press clippings from local and international publications document both Sharif's exhibitions and other art events are also included. The collection also includes an extensive series of photographic materials, comprising prints, slides, and negatives taken by Hussain Sharif between the 1980s and early 2000s. These images feature Sharif's artworks, Al Khor area of Dubai, outdoor scenes from the UAE and India, as well as artworks by other Emirati artists.
The materials were received in good condition, which enabled the digitization to take place at al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art, NYUAD. Digital surrogates were created for all collection items. Upon digitization, all materials were returned to the owner. Materials were rehoused in archival enclosures as needed.
E-records AD_MC_138
Scope and Contents
The Hussain Sharif Collection comprises a diverse range of exhibition materials, including press clippings, photographic materials, and other items, providing a detailed insight into Hussain Sharif's artistic practice and the evolution of the fine art scene in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) since the 1980s.
The exhibition materials include a significant collection of rare and valuable catalogs from some of the earliest fine art exhibitions in the United Arab Emirates (UAE). Highlights include several catalogs from the annual exhibition organized by the Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS), notably the catalog for the Society's inaugural exhibition held in Abu Dhabi in 1980. Additionally, the collection features other exhibition materials such as catalogs, brochures, and invitations pertaining to art exhibitions that took place in the UAE from the 1980s through the 2000s.
The collection also contains press clippings from local and international newspapers and magazines, which cover exhibitions and art events related to Hussain Sharif's work.
In addition to the exhibition materials and press clippings, the collection contains a comprehensive section of photographic materials, most of which were taken by Hussain Sharif. These materials include numerous prints of the Al Khor area in Dubai from the 1980s and 1990s, captured by the artist, as well as images of his artwork and a few prints from Sharif's travels to London and Berlin. Several sets of photographic slides are also included in the collection, most of which feature Hussain Sharif's artwork. Some slides depict outdoor scenes in the UAE and India in the 1980s and 1990s, along with artworks by other Emirati artists. Also included are a few strips of 35 mm negatives depicting various outdoor scenes in Dubai, taken by Hussain Sharif between the 1980s and 1990s.
Other items in the collection comprise a design for an art magazine created by Hussain Sharif, greeting cards featuring his artwork, and a brochure for a documentary project on Hassan Sharif.
Materials in the collection are primarily in Arabic, with some in English and French.
Biographical Note
Hussain Sharif (b. 1961) is a Dubai-based pioneering Emirati artist who was central to the development of conceptual arts in the United Arab Emirates. Alongside Emirati artists Hassan Sharif, Mohamed Yousif, Najat Makki, and others, Sharif was a founding member of the UAE's first art association, the Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS) in Sharjah, which established important social infrastructure that continues to foster collaborative communities of emerging artists. Sharif has spent his artistic career reimagining and adapting established techniques to reflect and embody his knowledge of his environment, giving new life to industrial materials and refuse like metal wire, cardboard, and paper scraps. Sharif's prolific and varied production of caricatures, paintings, installations, collages, and multimedia art has been widely exhibited in the UAE and internationally.
Born in 1961 in Dubai, Hussain Sharif was inspired to pursue art by the creative atmosphere cultivated at home by his older brother, the late artist Hassan Sharif, who is widely regarded as a pioneer of conceptual and performance art in the UAE. His participation in state-sponsored Arab youth camp programs as a student helped Sharif hone his artistic talent by allowing him to exhibit his work alongside other young artists from neighboring Arab countries. During his travels, Sharif explored the art scenes developing throughout the Gulf countries and the broader Arab world and learned from their style and technique. While still a student in high school, Sharif began drawing caricatures and, between 1975 and 1988, published them daily or weekly in local newspapers such as Al Wahda and Al Fajr newspapers in Abu Dhabi, and Al Khaleej published in Sharjah. Through publishing his work, Sharif was introduced to the journalism industry and built personal relationships with well-established caricature artists like Ali Ferzat, Salah al-Leithy, and Naji al-Ali, among others, and exhibited alongside them in joint caricature exhibitions in the UAE. Sharif held his first solo exhibition in 1981 at the Sharjah Cultural Club where he displayed his original caricature drawings. In 1979, artist Mohamed Yousif returned to the Emirates after receiving a formal art education in Cairo and, energized by his experiences, brought together a group of 16 artists, among them Sharif, to realize their goal of establishing the first art association in the UAE. In 1980, the Emirates Fine Arts Society was founded in Sharjah, sponsored by the Ministry of Information and Culture. The Emirates Fine Arts Society held its first annual exhibition in 1980 which saw the participation of 17 artists, including Hussain Sharif.
Sharif's interest in theatre grew organically through his proximity to Mohamed Yousif's work with the Sharjah National Theatre and, in 1983, he received a government scholarship to attend the High Institute of Kuwait. Sharif continued participating in local exhibitions while studying in Kuwait and, influenced by his brother, exhibited his first installation piece at the 1983 -/+ (Minus/Plus) exhibition held at Al Ahli Club in Dubai. Four years after the Emirates Fine Arts Society was established, they published the first issue of their art journal, Al Tashkeel, spearheaded by Hassan Sharif. The journal was a collection of opinion pieces commenting on prevalent art-related discourse, translations of essays on Western art history and art theory, book reviews, and news of cultural events in the UAE and the Arab world. Members of the Emirates Fine Art Society would participate in each issue's production, with Sharif editing and designing numerous issues. In 1986, Sharif graduated with a degree in theatre design and began working at Sharjah TV, eventually serving as their head designer from 1988 to 1996. Throughout the 1980s and 1990s, Sharif was part of a core collective of five artists who regularly exhibited together. While the group was sometimes joined by transitory artists, the foundational participants, the brothers Hassan and Hussain Sharif, Abdullah Al Saadi, Mohamed Kazem, and Mohamed Ahmed Ibrahim, became known informally as "the Five," after the 2002 exhibition titled 5 UAE held at the Ludwig Forum For International Art in Aachen, Germany.
In 2007, Abdulraheem Sharif, the brother of Hassan and Hussain, transformed his family home and a nearby warehouse into the Flying House, a joint exhibition and studio space and a substitute for Hassan's Satwa home, as a meeting place for artists, writers, and intellectuals to exchange ideas. Abdulraheem, alongside his brothers, Mohamed Kazem, and Dutch artist Jos Clevers, invested in the Flying House to combat the idea that prevailed in the artists' youth – that there was no contemporary art in the UAE. The Flying House, named after a painting by Clevers, now serves as a studio, gallery space, and documentation center for the contemporary art movement in the UAE.
Hussain Sharif exhibited widely throughout his career, both locally and internationally. He participated in most Emirates Fine Arts Society exhibitions and those held in collaboration with the Ministry of Information and Culture, local clubs, cultural centers, and galleries. Sharif also participated in international biennials including the 7th Cairo Biennale in 1998, the Dhaka Biennale in 2002, and numerous international exhibitions such as in Russia, Holland, France, Egypt, and Germany. Sharif also received multiple awards for his work, including the first prize for sculpture at the 1997 Sharjah International Art Biennale and the first prize at the Emirates Art Foundation portrait exhibition in 1998. His work is held in multiple public and private collections, including the Barjeel Art Foundation and the Sharjah Art Museum in Sharjah, the ADCO Oil Company in Abu Dhabi, the Commercial Banks of Dubai, and the Sittard Art Center in the Netherlands.
Custodial History
The materials in the Hussain Sharif Sharif collection were created and/or collected by the artist from the 1980s through the 2000s and have remained under his custody. In October 2024, the collection was loaned to al Mawrid at NYU Abu Dhabi for archival processing and digitization. Upon completion of the work at al Mawrid, the collection was returned to the artist in December 2024. Some sections of the collection were initially organized by the artist, which formed the basis for the detailed arrangement carried out by the team at al Mawrid.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: (I) Exhibition Materials (1980–2007); (II) Press Clippings; (III) Photographic Materials, and (IV) Other Items. Materials are subdivided into subseries by subject or type and arranged chronologically within each subseries.
Conditions Governing Access
Digital surrogates only are held by the repository. Based on the agreement with the owner, digital images of selected series/subseries will be publicly available on the NYU Archival Collections Finding Aid Portal. Materials not made available online may be consulted in person at al Mawrid, NYUAD. Researchers should contact nyuad.almawrid@nyu.edu to request details or to make an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Items were borrowed from Hussain Sharif for archival processing and digitization and returned upon completion.
Bibliography
1. Allison, Maya, Bana Kattan, Alaa Edris, and Adel Khozam. But We Cannot See Them: Tracing a UAE Art Community, 1988-2008. Edinburgh: Akkadia Press, 2017.
2. Al Qasimi, Hoor, and Karen Marta, eds. 1980-Today: Exhibitions in the United Arab Emirates. Abu Dhabi, UAE: National Pavilion United Arab Emirates la Biennale di Venezia, 2015.
3. Bidshahri, Yalda. "'Khaleej Modern.'" Artforum International, March 2023, 173–74.
4. Derderian, Elizabeth. "Challenging Terms: Contemporary Art and the Disciplining of Novelty in the UAE." Museum Anthropology 43, no. 2 (Fall 2020): 79–93. doi:10.1111/muan.12223.
5. Gronlund, Melissa. "Around the United Arab Emirates." ARTnews 116, no. 3 (Fall 2017): 138–41.
6. Jones, Kevin. "United Arab Emirates." ArtAsiaPacific, January 2, 2018, 178–81.
7. –. "Beyond Safe." ArtAsiaPacific, no. 93 (May 2015): 57–58.
8. Kholeif, Omar, and Candy Stobbs, eds. Imperfect Chronology: Arab Art from the Modern to the Contemporary: Works from the Barjeel Art Foundation. London: Whitechapel Gallery; Prestel, 2015.
9. Taylor, Woodman. "Negotiating New Dynamics. Navigating New Trails." International Gallerie 24, no. 2 (July 2021): 26–47.
10. Sharif, Hassan, Mohammed Ahmed Ibrahim, Mohammed Kazem, and Abdullah Al Saadi. "The Five: They Who Mapped the Way." International Gallerie 24, no. 2 (July 2021): 8–25.
11. Siegal, Nina. "The Foundations of Art in the Emirates." Modern Painters 31, no. 5 (May 2019): 116–19.
United Arab Emirates -- الإمارات العربية المتحدة; Abu Dhabi (United Arab Emirates) -- أبوظبي (الإمارات العربية المتحدة); Dubai (United Arab Emirates) -- دبي (الإمارات العربية المتحدة); Sharjah (United Arab Emirates) -- الشارقة (الإمارات العربية المتحدة); India -- الهند; Berlin (Germany) -- برلين (المانيا); Art -- Arab countries; Art, Arab -- 20th century; Art--Arab countries--20th century--Exhibitions -- الفن--الدول العربية --القرن العشرين--المعارض; Art, Arab -- الفن العربي; Art archives -- أرشيفات الفن; Art, Emirati -- الفن الإماراتي; Mixed media (Art) -- وسائط متعددة (فن); Assemblage (Art) -- تجميع خامات (فن); Found objects (Art) -- قطع متاحة (فن); Hassan Sharif (Emirati artist, 1951-2016) - حسن شريف (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٥١-٢٠١٦); Abdullah Al Saadi (Emirati artist, 1967- ) – عبد الله السعدي (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٦٧- ); Mohammed Ahmed Ibrahim (Emirati artist, 1962- ) – محمد أحمد إبراهيم (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٦٢- ); Abdul Qader Al Rais (Emirati artist, 1951- ) – عبد القادر الريس (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٥١- ); Mohamed Yousif (Emirati artist, 1953- ) – محمد يوسف (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٥٣- ); Mohammed Kazem (Emirati artist, 1969- ) – محمد كاظم (فنان إماراتي، ١٩٦٩- ); Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS), UAE – جمعية الإمارات للفنون التشكيلية; Cultural Foundation, Abu Dhabi – المجمّع الثقافي، أبوظبي; The French Alliance of Abu Dhabi – التحالف الفرنسي في أبوظبي; The French Institute in the United Arab Emirates – المعهد الفرنسي في الإمارات العربية المتحدة; Embassy of France in the United Arab Emirates – سفارة فرنسا في الإمارات العربية المتحدة; Al Tashkeel (magazine) – مجلة التشكيل; Al Khaleej (Newspaper) – صحيفة الخليج; Aletihad (newspaper) – صحيفة الاتحاد; Al Bayan (newspaper) – صحيفة البيان
- Series I: Exhibition Materials, (1980–2007)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I comprises catalogs, invitations, and brochures of various exhibitions held in the United Arab Emirates from the 1980s to the 2000s. This series includes materials from the annual exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS), along with materials from other solo and group exhibitions.
  - I.A. Annual Exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society, (1980–2005)
    This subseries contains exhibition materials pertaining to the annual exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS), including the catalog from the first exhibition held in 1980 in Abu Dhabi.
    - 1. "[ُThe First Exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society]," Abu Dhabi, 1980, cuid985
    - 2. "[The Second Exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society]," Sharjah, 1981, cuid986
    - 3. "[The Third Exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society]," Sharjah, 1982, cuid1264
    - 4. "[The Fourth Annual Exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society]," Sharjah, 1985, cuid987
    - 5. "[The Fifth Fine Arts Exhibition]," Sharjah, 1986, cuid988
    - 6. "[The Sixth Fine Arts Exhibition]," Sharjah, 1987, cuid989
    - 7. "[The Thirteenth Fine Arts Exhibition of the Emirates Fine Arts Society]," Sharjah, 1994, cuid990
    - 8. "[Interchange, the Emirates Fine Arts Society 24th Annual Exhibition]," Sharjah, 2005, cuid991
  - I.B. Other Exhibitions in the United Arab Emirates (UAE)
    This subseries includes materials from various solo and group exhibitions held in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) between the 1980s and 2000s. It features the brochure of Hassan Sharif's third solo exhibition, which took place in Sharjah in 1986, as well as the catalog from the exhibition of Hussain Sharif and Abdullah Al Saadi held in 1999. The Artists' Guide of the Emirates Fine Arts Society is also included.
    - 1. "[Third Solo Exhibition for the Artist Hassan Sharif]," Sharjah, 1986, cuid992
    - 2. "[Artists Guide of the Emirates Fine Arts Society]," Sharjah, 1980s, cuid993
    - 3. "[The Poster Exhibition]," Sharjah, 1980s, cuid994
    - 4. "[Solidarity Exhibition with the Lebanese and Palestinian Peoples]," Sharjah, 1980s, cuid995
    - 5. "[Fourth Spring Exhibition]," Abu Dhabi, 1990, cuid996
    - 6. "[Sharp Tools to Make Art: an Emirati Experiment, 1983-1995]," Sharjah, 1995, cuid997
    - 7. "Six Artists," Sharjah, 1996, cuid998
    - 8. "[Hussain Sharif – Abdullah Al Saadi]," Sharjah, 1999, cuid999
    - 9. "The Twentieth General Exhibition," Sharjah, 2001, cuid1000
    - 10. "7. U.A.E. Contemporary Art," Dubai, 2007, cuid1001
- Series II: Press Clippings
  Series II contains clippings from local newspapers, including al-Khaleej, Aletihad, and Albayan featuring articles and coverages related to Hussain Sharif's work. The series also includes clippings from Al Tashkeel art magazine published by the Emirates Fine Arts Society (EFAS).
  - II.A. Newspaper Clippings, cuid1002
  - II.B. Magazine Clippings, cuid1003
- Series III: Photographic Materials
  Series III comprises several sets of photographic prints, 35 mm slides, and a few strips of 35 mm negatives. The majority of the photographic materials were taken by Hussain Sharif and feature his artworks and exhibitions. Additionally, there are a few prints from Hussain Sharif's travels to London, Berlin, and Moscow, along with slides taken by Hussain Sharif during his travel to India in 1980-1981. This series also includes slides showcasing gatherings and group portraits in both indoor and outdoor settings.
  The series includes photographic prints of Al Khor in Dubai, also taken by Hussain Sharif in the 1980s and 1990s. These images were captured by the artist as inspirational scenes and as part of his exploration of the space and environment in which he lived.
  The arrangement of the photographic prints and slides followed the original order established by the artist. Several prints were mounted on white paper and placed inside plastic folders. The slides were housed in small plastic boxes, which the artist labeled with handwritten titles or annotations, primarily in Arabic. The titles given to the slide groups in subseries III.D. reflect the artist's handwritten annotations. In cases where slide boxes lacked handwritten notes, descriptive titles were assigned based on the subjects featured in the slides.
  - III.A. Personal Photographs
    - 1. London, cuid1004
    - 2. Berlin, cuid1005
    - 3. Moscow, cuid1265
    - 4. Other, cuid1266
  - II.B. Photographic Prints of Artworks, cuid1006
  - III.C. Photographs of Al Khor, Dubai (1980s–1990s), cuid1007
  - III.D. Photographs of Exhibitions
    - 1. "Exhibition of the Dubai Art Association," British Council, Dubai, 1975, cuid1267
    - 2. "Caricature," Central Public Library, Dubai, 1976, cuid1268
    - 3. "Emirates Fine Arts Society Fifth Annual Fine Arts Exhibition," Expo Centre Sharjah, 1986, cuid1269
    - 4. "Five Artists," Emirates Fine Arts Society, Sharjah, 1994, cuid1270
    - 5. "2nd Sharjah International Art Biennial," Sharjah, 1995, cuid1271
    - 6. "The Six," Sharjah Art Museum, Sharjah, 1996, cuid1272
    - 7. "U.A.E Artists," French Cultural Center, Dubai, 1997, cuid1273
    - 8. "Hussain Sharif - Abdullah Al Saadi," Sharjah, 1999, cuid1274
    - 9. "Solo Exhibition, 5th Sharjah International Art Biennial," Sharjah Art Museum, Sharjah, 2001, cuid1275
    - 10. "5 UAE," Ludwig Forum For International Art, Aachen, Germany, 2002, cuid1276
    - 11. 6th Sharjah International Art Biennial, Sharjah Expo Centre, Sharjah, 2003, cuid1277
  - III.E. Photographs Arranged by the Artist
    - 1. Drawings, Displayed at Home, 1975., cuid1278
    - 2. Artwork, early 1980s, cuid1279
    - 3. Collage Artwork, 1983-1985, cuid1280
    - 4. Collage Artwork, 1986-1989, cuid1281
    - 5. Paintings, early 1990s, cuid1282
    - 6. Installation Work, Photographed at Home, Later Exhibited at the Sharjah Biennial, 1997, cuid1283
    - 7. Artwork on Exhibit, 1998, cuid1284
    - 8. Faces, 1998, cuid1285
    - 9. Installation Work, Photographed at the Open Studio in Deira, 1998, cuid1286
    - 10. Installation Work, photographed at home, 2001, cuid1287
    - 11. Vernacular Photography of Dubai, c. 2009, cuid1288
  - III.F. Slides
    - 1. Outdoor Scenes Taken by Hussain Sharif, India, 1980-1981, cuid1008
    - 2. "[Collage]," 1982-1990, cuid1289
    - 3. Taken by Hussain Sharif and His Friends, 1980s–1990s, cuid1009
    - 4. "[Hussain Sharif]," late 1980s - early 1990s, cuid1290
    - 5. Outdoor Scenes Taken by Hussain Sharif, UAE, 1990s, cuid1010
    - 6. "[Collage, Mixed Media]," 1990-1995, cuid1291
    - 7. "[Gypsum, Different Materials, and Medals, 1997]", cuid1011
    - 8. "[Cement/Tin Cans, 2001]", cuid1012
    - 9. "Strike, 2002", cuid1013
    - 10. "[Faces, Tin Cans, and Drawings on the Walls]," Undated, cuid1014
    - 11. "[Hussain's Paintings, Carton, and Different Materials]," Undated, cuid1015
    - 12. "[Collage, Tin Cans, Three-dimensional, and Carton Artworks]," Undated, cuid1016
    - 13. "[Collage/Environment, and Acrylic]," Undated, cuid1017
    - 14. "[Pastel/Environment]," Undated, cuid1018
    - 15. "[Abstract/Oil, Acrylic, and Pastel]," Undated, cuid1019
    - 16. "[Artists' works: Hassan, Mohamed Youssef, Abd Al Qader, and Others]," Undated, cuid1020
    - 17. "Collage Slides," Undated, cuid1292
    - 18. "[Art and Environment]," Undated, cuid1293
    - 19. "Collage Artwork," after 1987 ??, cuid1294
    - 20. "Collage, Oil, and Mixed Media," Undated, cuid1295
    - 21. "[Work on Slide]," Undated, cuid1296
  - III.G. Negatives, cuid1021
    Strips of 35 mm negatives featuring various outdoor scenes in Dubai, taken by Hussain Sharif between 1980s–1990s.
- Series IV: Other Items
  - IV.A. Greeting Cards, cuid1022
    Greeting cards featuring paintings by Hussain Sharif.
  - IV.B. Art Magazine Design by Hussain Sharif, cuid1023
    A design for an art magazine titled "[Arts]," created by Hussain Sharif in 1998. The magazine includes several contributions on art subjects, such as an article on Mohamed Ahmed Ibrahim by Hassan Sharif.
  - IV.C. A Brochure of a Documentary on Hassan Sharif, cuid1024
    A brochure for a documentary project on Hassan Sharif, directed by Valsalan Kanara in 2006.